<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints privilege, or, Gain by dying</title>
            <author>Scott, Chr. (Christopher), fl. 1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39520</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18425799</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18425799</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107602</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107602)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1643:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints privilege, or, Gain by dying</title>
                  <author>Scott, Chr. (Christopher), fl. 1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 29 [i.e. 30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed :</publisher>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Chr. Scott.</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 26-27 misnumbered 28-25, p. 30 misnumbered 29.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: slightly faded, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians I, 21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107602:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107602:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS PRIVILEDGE, OR GAIN by DYING.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Gaudium, ſuper omne gaudium, vincens omne gaudium, extra quod non eſt gaudium, quando intrabo in te, ut videam Deum meum qui habitat in te?</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auſt.</hi> de deſiderio &amp; ſiti animae ad Deum.</bibl>
               <p>O mora, Chriſte veni,</p>
               <p>Mors pijs, malorum ademptio, bonorum adeptio, Diſce mori, ſurſum quiſquis ſapis erige vultum in patriam, terras deſpice, diſce mori.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2.</bibl>
               <p>We groan earneſtly, deſiring to be cloathed upon with our houſe which is from Heaven.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:107602:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107602:2"/>
            <head>To my much Honoured, and Worthy Friend, Captain <hi>Robert Fiſher.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Would be loath to be the firſt that welcomes You into <hi>England,</hi> with the ſad Newes of the breach that God hath (ſince your departure) made upon your comforts, I mean, in taking to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf your dear Wife. I ſuppoſe the tidings of that, will reach your eares to your hearts greif before my Papers, for bad newes flyes apace. I ſend you not theſe Lines for that end, but for a contrarie, namely, rather to quiet and bare up your diſconſolate Spirit under ſo ſmarting a Providence: As a meanes to which, I commend to you a ſerious conſideration of her great Gain, to be oppoſed to your great loſs: what great gainers Chriſts Saints are by Dying, you may, if you pleaſe, read in the following Lines.</p>
            <p>Sir, I remember one ſayes that the work of Navigation, is a very great Work; and requires much <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and Wiſdome, for men to build moveable Houſes, and go thorough the great Deep, or dry Land, and every way ſo fitted as would amuſe an ordinary and unskilfull beholder to view. Its a very graet work, Now God that hath brought you lately from doing one great work, hath upon your return provided another for you to do. Which is to ſubmit and reſolve your will into his, and if I miſtake not to do this aright, will ask you no leſs <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and Wiſdom, I am ſure more Grace and Holineſs, then the former; but that God that hath given you underſtanding for the one, can by his Almighty Power and Goodneſs, inable you to the other.</p>
            <p>You have often ſeen in the Seas, the reſemblance of the miſery of mans life, as that ebbeth and floweth, and is ſeldom quiet, but after a little calm a ſtorm ſucceeds, why ſuch is the whole life on Land too, nought elſe but a Sea of Tempeſts while on this ſide our great Haven or Port of Glory.</p>
            <p>Its the ſaying of a Learned and good Man; what pitty is it but Souldiers and Marriners ſhould be holy Perſons, who are ſo ſubject to dangers, and have ſuch experiences of Gods Goodneſs
<pb facs="tcp:107602:3"/>and Mercy in their preſervation: He that carryes his life in his hand, ſhould alwayes carry grace in his heart, and yet the Author complaines, who worſe men then thoſe that behold Gods wonders in the Deep. Seldome good but in a Storm, and when over as bad or worſe then ever: of Souldiers it was long ſince an harſh affirmation, <hi>Nulla fides pietaſque viris qui caſtra ſequuntur,</hi> I wiſh the moſt of them did not too much verify it, that there is little Religion or Piety in ſuch as follow Camps; and of Marriners <hi>Nautarum vota,</hi> a Marriners Vow, hath been long ſince a Proverb, and yet ſome very good men amongſt both ſorts: for Souldiers, we read of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius,</hi> of whom tis ſayd he was a devout Man, one that feared God with all his Houſe, gave much Almes and prayed to God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, and he was a juſt man, one that feared God, and of good Report, <hi>Acts. 10.2.22,</hi> and <hi>v. 7.</hi> of the ſame Chapter, <hi>You read of a devout Souldier that belong'd to that devout Captain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for Seamen and Marriners; I queſtion not but God hath a large and precious number among them, of which I hope your ſelf to be one, and that you ſeriouſly deſire ſo to be: and truly Sir, if ſo, as I queſtion it not, here is a tryal for you, to make proof of, and make uſe of that Faith, that Patience, that Humility and ſelf De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal, yea of that whole ſtock of divine Grace, wherewith God hath endowed and enriched your Soul.</p>
            <p>I have read of <hi>Alexander,</hi> when he was in a great Perill in <hi>India,</hi> being to fight with Men and Beaſts, huge Elephants; he ſolaced and cheered himſelf, ſaying <hi>Tandem par animo meo periculum video,</hi> at length I ſee a danger anſwerable to my mind, as great Dangers require great Stomaches; ſo great Tryals will exerciſe great Graces, I hope you have learned not to deſpiſe the chaſtning of the Lord, nor faint when rebuked of him, as knowing <hi>that whom the Lord loveth he chaſtneth, and ſcourgeth every ſon whom he receiveth,</hi> Heb. <hi>12.5, 6.</hi> I muſt needs yeild your loſs very great, for I think in my heart, no man ever enjoy'd a more tender, kind, loving, and every way endearing, and deſirable yoke fellow; For her Piety towards God, her love to your ſelf, and all excellent endowments, you had wives in a Wife, truly Sir, did I not really believe it I would not dare to ſpeak it, <hi>I know not how to give f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>attering Titles, in ſo doing my Maker might ſoon take me away,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hugo Card.</note> Job <hi>32.22.</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a Learned writer, upon thoſe words of <hi>David, Pſ. 39.1. That I ſin not with my tongue, I will keep my mouth with a Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> &amp;c, <hi>makes eleven</hi> ſeveral wayes, wherein a man may be guilty,
<pb facs="tcp:107602:3"/>and offend in ſpeech; as lying, detracting, ſwearing, idle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> amongſt the reſt of tongue vices, he reckons up that of flattery, thereby intimating, that Chriſtians ought as well to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of this, as of any of the other: and ſayes one, <hi>Amarae ſunt oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentium linguae, &amp; non ſemper veratia ſunt ora laudantium;</hi> the tongues of Detractours are bitter, and the tongues of Flatterers of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes not true, but that God that ponders hearts as well as words; knowes that I really think all true, that I ſpeak or have ſpoken of her.</p>
            <p>And therefore your loſs the grater, but Sir, quarrell not that you enjoyed her no longer, but bleſs God you enjoyed her ſo long, and be content that he hath her, who hath more intereſt in her then your ſelf ever had, to whom ſhe was but lent for a little while,</p>
            <p>And now learn by her loſs, how ſlippery the beſt of earthly comforts are, and therefore to look at, to look after, and make ſure of; theſe comforts that when enjoyed are never to be parted with; look up to that place where ſhe in her better part dwels, where there is life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out death, day without night, joyes without ſorrowes, holineſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out impurity, comforts without croſſes, reſt without labour, health without ſickneſs, youth without age, beauty without deformity, ſtrength without weakneſs; where are ſuch good things as <hi>Eye ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</note>
               <hi>Ear never heard,</hi> or <hi>Heart never comprehended;</hi> and to compleat all, eternity of all, without change or fear of loſs.</p>
            <p>When once we are got ſafe thither, we ſhall be ſafe indeed; yea ſit down and be quiet, which this troubleſome (yet bewitched world) will not afford us: thither I hope you aſpire, whither ſhe is but gone before.</p>
            <p>I have no more, but to end with my well wiſhes, beſeeching God to bleſs, guide, and keep you; to fill you with himſelf, to ſtay your mind up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf, to enable you to make a wiſe and holy improvement of this ſtroake, and to ſay, <hi>what ſhall I receive good at the hand of the Lord, and not evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord continue you a comfort to yours, and make them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts to you, and make your little Daughter the Relict of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Yoke-fellow, the inheritrix of her Mothers Vertues; that all her excellent endowments, may ſo live and flouriſh in that little child of hers; that we may ſay of her gone, as <hi>Cicero</hi> of his <hi>Sulpitius,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Null<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m monumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum clarius Sulpitius relinquere potuit quam effigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em morum ſuorum, virtutis, conſtantiae, pictatis, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genij fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> he could not have left a better monument, than ſo lively a Portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his goodneſs in his Son.</p>
            <p>I hope Sir, you will pardon me the giving you this trouble, and let the ſingular respect I bear to your ſelf, and the honour I owe to the memory of your pious Conſort, now with God, plead my excuſe I have no more but to aſſure you of my being and remaining</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Cordial Friend and Servant in CHRIST JESUS</hi> Chr. Scott.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study in</hi> Milton Hamlet,
<date>
                     <hi>this 3.</hi> Ian. <hi>1672.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:107602:4"/>
            <head>To my Worthy and much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Friends. Captain <hi>John Bradman,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Sarah Bradman</hi> his Wife. Friends &amp; Relations to
<list>
                  <item>Captain <hi>Richard Haddock</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Iſaack Heath.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Richard Fiſher</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Brothers in Law to Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Fiſher.</hi> Daughter in Law to Mrs. <hi>Marjory Fiſher,</hi> late VVife to Captain <hi>Robert Fiſher,</hi> together with the reſt of her Pious Relations and Friends, whether to Me Known or Unknown.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Chriſtian and Worthy Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>UNderſtanding it was the great deſire of your dear Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman and my loving friend Mrs. <hi>Fiſher,</hi> that (if it might have been) I ſhould have preached Her Funerall Sermon; and hearing by ſome after your comming down, that your deſign was, that rather then her deſire ſhould not be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, to have had it done in private, Though for my own part, I thought it not convenient by reaſon of the multitude of people, which could not have received benefit, and the offence that might have been taken; yet had it not been otherwiſe reſolved, but her requeſt had been inſiſted upon, I muſt have ſubmitted to any inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,
<pb facs="tcp:107602:4"/>rather then not have anſwered her and your deſires. In or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to which, after I heard of it, I applyed my ſelf that little time I had to the work: but very glad that it was at laſt performed by another in publick, where no offence could be given, or danger incurred.</p>
            <p>And now becauſe I could not ſerve her and your deſires in that laſt office, yet in the Teſtification of my great reſpects I owe to her memory and your ſelves her dear relations; I have thought good to copy out my then prepared Meditations; and in theſe few ſheets of Paper to preſent you with them, as to ſerve, for an acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my thankfulneſs to you all, for your reſpects ſhewed to me, a Stranger to you, and undeſerving from you, ſo to teſtify my great eſteem of that precious Saint of Chriſt, and to let all that ſhall read them ſee, that ſuch loſſes are deeply to be lamented. I cannot ſay they are word for word the ſame, but as near as poſſible the ſame, they ſhould have been if I had then preached them, perhaps although not for any worth in them, yet for her reſpect, whoſe death hath occaſioned them, you may at ſome ſpare hours, caſt an eye upon them, and if they may be matter of advantage to your ſelves, or any other, I ſhould be glad, being joyfull I might ſerve or do good to any that belonged to her, though unknown to me. I believe you all affectionately loved her and delighted in her, truly the beſt and now the only way left to teſtify your reſpect of her, is to ſet before your eyes, and keep in your memoryes the Pious example of her holy life, and to be followers of her ſo far as ſhe was of Chriſt Jeſus, a Copy with fewer blots, a rule leſs crooked, I know not where you will find on this ſide heaven.</p>
            <p>The work that ſhe hath done, I know you expect to do, leave her, and prepare for your own; that when Chriſt comes he may find you no worſe prepared, then I hope he found her; to this end let matters of ſoul-concernment, which are the only buſineſs of life, have more, and matters of the world have leſs of your hours then ever they have had. Its ſtrange to ſee how this vain world, where we can be but a very little time at longeſt, ſhould ſo eat up our Affections, Thoughts, Deſires, Dayes, and Years; that for the one thing needfull, we can find no leiſure, as if our God, our Chriſt, our Souls, our Heaven, were nothing worth.</p>
            <p>It was an excellent speech of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth to the Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> who when he had ſhewed him the glory of his Princely Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and earthly Paradiſe, inſtead of admiring it, or him for it,
<pb facs="tcp:107602:5"/>he only returned him this grave and ſerious Anſwer <hi>haec ſunt quae faciunt invitos mori;</hi> theſe are the things that make us unwilling to Dye; ſo truly this is the great cauſe, why Chriſtians play loath to depart, when their times come, and make death ſuch a Bug-bare, they have been, with <hi>Martha,</hi> combred with much ſerving, alwayes ſo buſied about laying up Treaſures that they muſt now leave behind them; that they are unprovided of that which ſhould ſerve them for their great Journey; Oh my friends when you are Bees for Earth, but Drones for Heaven, what low thoughts have you of it?</p>
            <p>Methinks is an Incongruous ſight, if we could ſee in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o it, that a man who is <hi>animal brevis aevi,</hi> ſhould be <hi>infinitae Sol icitudinis,</hi> a creature but of a dayes continuance in the world, yet of infinite cares about the world; and what is this world we purſue? as one ſayes,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Vita quid eſt homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num? vaſti quid gloria mundi? Dulla eſt &amp; ſomnus fumus &amp; umbra fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gax.</note> what is this life? what is the glory of this vaſt world? a Bubble, a Dream, a little Smoake, a flying Shadow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And yet what Folly and Madneſs poſſeſſeth the hearts of men,</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. <hi>9.3.</hi> to do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e on this windy Bubble, to pleaſe themſelves with this fooliſh Dream, to embrace this blacking Smoake, and ever to bee catching at this flying Shadow, till with <hi>Eſops</hi> Dog the ſubſtance be loſt and paſt recovery.</p>
            <p>But I hope better things of you whom I write, you are not to Learn in point of knowledge, how to diſtinguiſh of things that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; and I hope it need not be preſſed in point of practiſe, to looke not at things ſeen but at things not ſeen; All I ſhall ſay to you, ſhall be but this, as you would not have your Sun ſet in a Cloud, I mean Dye uncheerfully, for your ſelves; as you would not ſadden the hearts of your ſurviving Godly friends; as you would not bring up an evil report upon the Proteſtant Faith, which you profeſs, which teacheth Chriſtians that aſſurance of Salvation may be had; as you would not open the mouths of the wicked to caſt dirt upon holyneſs, when they ſee the profeſſours of it go to death with Reluctancies; as you would prevent all this, make Religion your great buſineſs, that ſo when your dying hours come, your Souls may be full of ſweet peace and comfort; live as ſtrangers in this world, and perſons belonging to another, that you may be willing and ready to remove and go home, when God ſhall ſend for you, which that you may be, ſhall be the earneſt Deſire and Prayer of him who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Soul Friend and Servant in CHRIST,</hi> Chr. Scott.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From My Study in</hi> Milton Hamlet, <hi>this</hi>
                  <date>3d January, <hi>1672.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107602:5"/>
            <head>Philippians 1.21. Latter part of the Verſe, <hi>And to dye, gain.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>The whole verſe runs thus,</hi> For me to live is Chriſt, and to dye, gain.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Particle cauſal, (for) which ſtands in the front of the verſe, bids us to look back to ſomething that went before to make the ſenſe perfect; and ſome Expoſitors lead us a good way back for the cohaerence of the words: But I ſhall not go any farther then the words immediately preceding, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Apoſtle had declared his willingneſs either for life or death, ſo Chriſt might in either be glorified by him. And now as a reaſon of that profeſſion or reſolution, he comes in with theſe words; <hi>For me to live is Chriſt, and to dye, gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the whole Verſe obſerve theſe two parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Chriſtians duty in theſe words, <hi>To me to live is Christ.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Chriſtians priveledge in the laſt words, <hi>and to dye gain.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Or thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is the believers aim and ſcope while he lives, and that is Chriſt, either
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The glory of Chriſt.</hi> or,</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The enjoyment of Christ.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is bleſſedneſs when he dyes, he that liveth with Chriſt or unto Chriſt while he lived, he can't be a loſer when he dyes; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have loſt for Chriſt, but never any loſt by Chriſt; no, ſooner or later, living or dying, Chriſt will make up all his loſſes, to ſuch a one, to dye, is gain.</p>
            <p>Or yet again, if you pleaſe I ſhall reſolve the words into three general parts thus, and there reſt:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. You have a great and gracious priveledge, and that is gain by dying, tis not the lott of all to have death an advantage, and therefore I call it a priveledge, and a great one.</item>
               <item>2, You have the Apoſtles confidence of it in particular to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in this particle <hi>me, to me to dye is gain,</hi> as he ſayes 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>there is layd up for</hi> me <hi>a Crown,</hi> ſo <hi>to me to dye is gain,</hi> it would be little advantage to know that others ſhall gain by dying, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107602:6"/>I can affirm it of my ſelf, <hi>to me to dye is gain.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. You have this probation, (as I may ſo call it) of his right to this priveledge, that it was not a thread-bare hope, as the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of moſt is, in theſe words, <hi>to me to live is Chriſt,</hi> and if to me to live be Chriſt, then to me to dye muſt be gain, <hi>to me to live is Chriſt, and to dye gain.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>There is nothing of difficulty in the words, only I confeſs I meet with various readings of them amongſt Expoſiters, though no ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great or material difference; as for example.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beza</hi> reads the words thus, <hi>Mihi enim eſt Chriſtus &amp; in vita &amp; in morte lucrum,</hi> Chriſt is to me gain, both in life and in death, and ſayes, that as in the former words, <hi>v.</hi> 20. ſo in theſe which are a reaſon of them, Chriſt is the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus eſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triuſque membri ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jectum.</note> ſubject of each part, and gain the praedicate thus, Chriſt is my gain in life, and Chriſt is my gain in death, <hi>Gualt.</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, to me in life and death, Chriſt is gain; that is ſayes he<note n="(b)" place="margin">Haec eſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta mea ſi Chriſtum videam glorificari, &amp;c.</note> this is my life, If I may but ſee Chriſt glorified whether I live or whether I dye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tremellius</hi> reads the words thus<note n="(d)" place="margin">Vita mea Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, &amp; ſi moriar lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum eſt mihi.</note>
               <hi>Chriſt is my life, and if I dye, my gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Piſcator</hi> reads it wholly according to the vulgar Tranſlation; the words ſaies he are <hi>ratio diſtributionis propoſitae,</hi> a reaſon of the diſtribution foregoing, and that is plain, by the particle cauſal (for) and ſaies, 'tis as if the Apoſtle had ſaid, Chriſt ſhall be glorified in my body if I live, <hi>for to me to live is Chriſt,</hi> that is, all the actions of my life and ſufferings of it too, do and ſhall tend to his glory; but if otherwiſe that I dye and be killed for his ſake, even my death alſo ſhall not only redound to his glory, but to my own gain and advantage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zanch.</hi> his gloſs the ſame with this in effect, which reading ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you follow, the doctrine that I ſhall lay down, will naturally flow from the Text.</p>
            <p>I intend onely to ſpeak to the latter part of the verſe; namely, to theſe words, <hi>(and to dye gain)</hi> and there are two points that I might commend unto you from the ſame, the firſt more general, which is this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>1</label> Even thoſe that are moſt dear to Chriſt, muſt yet dye a natural death, good or bad, if ſons of <hi>Adams;</hi> the <hi>Statutum eſt</hi> is gone forth, they cannot be exempted, 'tis appointed to man once to dye; Man, that is every man, indefinite propoſitions are aequivolent to uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal: 'tis true in reſpect of deaths conſequences, the Saints have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107602:6"/>advantage of the wicked, as I hope to your comfort, and their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakening to make good; but in reſpect of deaths paſſage they are equally ſharers, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.16. <hi>how dyeth the wiſe man? even as the fool.</hi> But that is not the point intended; again 2dly. the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine I intend is this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> All thoſe that belong to Chriſt, they gain by dying, all ſuch to whom to live is Chriſt, to them to dye ſhall be gain; if you pleaſe take it thus,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> The Saints of God, whenever or however they dye, they ſtill change for the better; they gain by their change, thoſe that have made Chriſt their aim, the glory of Chriſt living to him, the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt he living in them, to all theſe, death ſhall be a gain.</p>
            <p>Believers, gain by dying, that's the point I have to make good.</p>
            <p>How full are the Scriptures of pertinent teſtimonies for the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting of this comfortable truth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1. <hi>The righteous periſheth.</hi> How periſheth? God forbid, their is terrour in that expreſſion; the words following are a correction, a ſweetning of that ſeemingly bitter expreſſion, tis a good periſhing, <hi>they are taken away from the evil to come, enter into peace, reſt in their beds, &amp;c.</hi> ſo 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <hi>We know that if our earthly houſe of this tabernacle be diſſolved,</hi> if it be? does the Apoſtle make a Scruple of that? no, for down it muſt, nothing more certain; but if it be, that is, when it ſhall be, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; what then? we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands eternal in the Heavens; theſe mud-wall houſes, whoſe foundation is in the duſt, which we keep ſuch a do to patch up, and all our patching will not long ſerve neither, they muſt, they will down; well, and let them down; we ſhall get by it, our dwelling will be well mended, we ſhall have a beter houſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hence <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.1. <hi>the day of death is better then the day of birth.</hi> The one the out-let from, the other the inlet to, a world of little eaſe, leſs comfort. St. <hi>Paul</hi> knew there was good by dying, elſe ſo wiſe a man would never have deſired it; <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved.</hi> And ſaies one upon the place, A good man<note n="(a)" place="margin">Vitam in patientia mortem in deſiderio.</note> hath life in patience, but death in deſire: well pleaſed to live, but better pleaſed to dye. Surely were there not ſome advantage to be made by dying it would not be matter of choice and option.</p>
            <p>But for the proſecuting this point, I ſhall do but theſe two things.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:107602:7"/>
            <list>
               <item>1. Shew in what reſpects beleivers gain by the change of death. And</item>
               <item>2. Apply it for our own advantage, preſent and future.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt thing, and that is to ſhew in what reſpects beleivers gain by this change of death; and this I ſhall hold out unto you but in theſe three particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In the change of their place.</item>
               <item>2. In the change of their eſtate.</item>
               <item>3. In the change of their company.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Look upon them in any, or all theſe reſpects, and death makes the Saints of Chriſt great gainers.</p>
            <p>Firſt they gain in the change of their place, and this I ſhall hold out unto you in theſe four things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt they change Earth for Heaven, is not that a gain, <hi>John</hi> 17.26. <hi>Father I will that they whom thou haſt given me, may be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory.</hi> You know where Chriſt is, <hi>he is in Heaven, Acts</hi> 3.21. why then dying, they muſt be there too, for they muſt be where he is, he told his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples when he left them, he went but to prepare a place for them <hi>in thoſe manſions in his Fathers houſe,</hi> and when he had done, that he <hi>would come again, and receive them to himſelf, that where he was they might be alſo, John.</hi> 14.2.3. Now what a change is here, is not this gain beloved? only here is the miſchief, we know what Earth is, we don't yet know what Heaven is, as St. <hi>John</hi> ſayes, <hi>it does not yet appear what we ſhall be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2.</note> otherwiſe I am perſwaded we would not care how ſoon death did us that happy and good turn, but ſo long as we live here on earth, look as it fared with Chriſt's Diſciples, when they ſtood looking upon their Lords aſcending, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.9. <hi>While they beheld he was taken up, and a cloud received him out of their ſight;</hi> there was a cloud that parted him above, and them below, ſo there are clouds between our heaven and us, we can't ſee into it, and therefore know not how good 'tis being in it; all we can get ſight of it, but a few glimpſes and ſparklings, and that but now and then, of that Royal City; if the Coeleſtial excellencies, and ſurpaſſing joyes, of that glorious bliſs and bliſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful glory,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.14.</note> were but apparent, we ſhould quickly cry as <hi>Peter</hi> in the transfiguration, <hi>oh good being there,</hi> come death, if thy gain be ſuch, even when thou wilt; that's the firſt thing, they change Earth for Heaven, place well amended.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They change a bloody field for a place of triumph, what is this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107602:7"/>life, but a continual combate? this world but a place of blood? wars and rumours of wars, are the dayly tidings of the poor chriſtian; ſcarrs and wounds the frequent badges of chriſtianity; look into the Scriptures and you frequently read of warring, fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſtriving, chriſtians reſembled to ſouldiers, and bid alwayes to go harneſt; will you ſee a few expreſſions to this purpoſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18. <hi>I charge thee Son</hi> Timothy <hi>that thou war a good warfare,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.3. <hi>Endure hardneſs, as a good Souldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 1 Tim. 6.12. <hi>Fight the good fight of Faith,</hi> yea, as if they were never to be out of the field ſo long as here they are bidden, Eph. 6.12.13, 14. <hi>To put on the whole armour of God, and with their loyns girt, &amp;c.</hi> Tis true, wicked men, they know not what a conflict means; what a conflict with the world means, <hi>they are of the world,</hi> Joh. 15.19. <hi>and therfore the world loves its own;</hi> what a conflict with Satan means, they are his, John 8.44. <hi>Ye are of your Father the Devil;</hi> and though I cannot ſay he loves them, yet he is quiet with them ſo long as he keeps the houſe, rules the roaſt, all is peace, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.21. what a conflict with their luſts means; their luſts and they are agreed, what a war between fleſh and ſpirit means, they conſiſt but of a ſingle principle, yea but God's people can't be thus quiet, no, the world is to them a right warfar: but now comes death, and that puts an end to all theſe bloody battles, takes them away from this bloody field, and whither but to a place of triumph, ſee 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7.8. <hi>I have fought my fight, I have fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht my courſe, and henceforth is laid up for me a crown,</hi> no more fights now, &amp;c. And that's a ſecond peice of their gain in reference to the place, this is a good change, a feild of blood for a place of triumph.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> They change a place of baniſhment, for their own countrey, a place where they are but ſtrangers and pilgrims, for their fathers houſe, <hi>I am a ſojourner and ſtranger before thee, as all my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were,</hi> ſayes the Prophet ſpeaking of this life; tis true,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.12.</note> they have a countrey of their own, where they have a rich and glorious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; there is a kingdome they belong to, but its above, no ſight of it but what the eye of faith gives them;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7</note> we walk by faith and not by ſight; <hi>in my fathers houſe are many Manſions,</hi> yea, but they are held from them, hid from them, for the preſent; the ſaints here are far from home, from their countrey, their friends, kindred and alliance, they are above; but now comes death, and that carryes them home into their countrey, to their fathers houſe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107602:8"/>
               <hi>that inheritance of the Saints in light. Coll.</hi> 1.12. while we are at home in the body we are abſent from the Lord; but now they ſhall go home to their Father from a ſtrange countrey, where they have met with nothing but injuries and oppreſſions; where they have been neither known nor valued according to their worth, but the precious ſons of <hi>Sion</hi> yet eſteemed as earthen pitchers, where they have been hated and hooted at; <hi>Behold I and the children whom thou haſt given me are for ſignes and wonders, Eſa.</hi> 8.18. they ſhall go now where they are known, honour'd, priz'd ſhining forth in the glory of their Father. As a Kings Son and Heir to a Crown, travelling in a ſtrange countrey under a diſguiſe, no more ſet by then an ordinary man; but coming home to his Fathers Court, there he is honoured: why thus will it fare with the Saints if once death be ſent for them, and in that reſpect gain by dying, in reference to the place they change for.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And laſtly, they change a valley of tears and waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> for a place that knowes not what a tear means: how often is it the voice of a Saint, while be lives here, my tears have been my meat day and night, you know what the Pſalmiſt ſayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5. <hi>They that ſow in tears, &amp;c.</hi> and he that goeth forth weeping, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating that our ſeed time is very watery; what is this world but a Bochim? a place of weeping; to have a gracious heart and not wet cheeks, are almoſt inconſiſtent; ſo many occaſions of weeping meet the Saints withall, that they can't long keep dry eyes; tears for offending God, tears for preſent and frequent loſſes of their belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, tears for the ſins of others, whereby God is diſhonoured; <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of tears guſh out of mine eyes becauſe they keep not thy Law, Pſal.</hi> 119.136. tears for the ſufferings and oppreſſions of the Church, and people of God; <hi>By the waters of</hi> Babylon <hi>we ſate down, and wept when wee remembred</hi> Sion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.1. Some occaſion or other ſtill furniſhing them with matter of new and freſh ſorrows; yea but now comes death, and that carryes them from this weeping countrey, and ſets them in a place where tears and ſorrows are not known, Rev. 21.4. <hi>God ſhall wipe away all tears, there ſhall be no more death, nor ſorrow, nor crying, nor pain;</hi> Oh what a change is here: And thus you ſee that in all theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, believers gain by dying in the change of their place.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2dly."/> Then ſecondly, as they better themſelves by dying in reſpect of the place, ſo alſo in reſpect of their eſtate and condition, in this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107602:8"/>reſpect alſo Death makes them great gainers; and this I ſhall hold out unto you in theſe five particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> They change labour and travel, for reſt and peace, what is a mans life while here, but labour, ſorrow and ſweat, <hi>All things are full of labour,</hi> Eccleſ. 1.8. God ſent no man hither to be idle; this life is for working, if he will have his hands <hi>full</hi> though but of earth, <hi>it ſhall be with travel and vexation of ſpirit,</hi> Eccleſ. 4.6. Yea, <hi>ſore travel hath God given to the ſons of men to be exerciſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</hi> Eccleſ. 1.13. wouldſt thou have bleſſings temporal, or wouldſt thou have bleſſings ſpiritual; neither will come with ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſtill: the man in purſuite of the former, he is up early, a bed late, and eats the bread of carefulneſs; and the Chriſtian that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues the latter, he carryes them not with a few yawning wiſhing, no he muſt digg and delve for theſe too; if thou cryeſt after know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>If thou ſeekeſt her as ſilver, and ſearcheſt for her as for hidden treaſures,</hi> Prov. 2.3, 4. Would he have ſalvation?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.24. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.19. <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.11.</note> he muſt work for it, <hi>work out your ſalvation, ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait gate, give diligence to make your calling and election ſure:</hi> what bleſſings ſoever you look at, tis the diligent hand that maketh rich; and while life laſteth, mans labour and travel will not end; to be ſure, not the Saints, whoever take their eaſe, they muſt not, their work is too great to ſit down and ſing the fools <hi>requiem, Soul, take thyne eaſe:</hi> Yea but now death finiſhes all their labour and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and puts them to reſt, though they could not have a ſitting time on earth, yet now they <hi>ſhall ſit down with</hi> Abraham <hi>and</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob <hi>in the kingdome of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rev. 14.13. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, they reſt from their labours,</hi> and Heb. 4.4. <hi>there remains a reſt for the people of God,</hi> though they have it not here, they ſhall have it, it remains for them; what ever travel or trouble awaites their life, their end is peace, Pſal. 37.37. <hi>Mark the upright man, behold the juſt, the end of that man is peace;</hi> if once death comes then they reſt; bodies reſt, and ſouls reſt, bodyes reſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.2. They <hi>enter into peace, and reſt in their beds;</hi> yea and ſouls reſt too, if <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome be a reſting place. Well that's the firſt thing, I think you'l call this a gain by dying, their condition is much bettered, from labour and travel to reſt and peace; but then</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They change corruption and mortality, for incorruption and immortality;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15.</note> 1 Cor. 15.53. <hi>This corruptible muſt put on incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and this mortal muſt put on immortality;</hi> while here they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107602:9"/>are alwayes in fear of death, which is a <hi>bondage</hi> as the Apoſtle calls it, at leaſt in expectation of it; yea but then mortality ſhall be ſwallowed up of life, and no more dying fears, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54. <hi>When this corruption ſhall have put on incorruption, and this mortal ſhall have put on immortality, then ſhall be brought to paſs that ſaying which is written, death is ſwallowed up in victory:</hi> while here, what crazy bodyes do we carry about us? alwayes a dying and drawing on; yea but when we come above, they ſhall have <hi>impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam moriendi,</hi> be under an impoſſibility of dying, though as the learned obſerve, not <hi>abſolutam &amp; naturalem;</hi> for ſo God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly immortal, he only hath an abſolute and natural impoſſibility of dying; but <hi>ex gratia doni,</hi> by the free gift and good pleaſure of God, our bodies put under an impoſſibility of dying any more; and in this reſpect better with us, then it ſhould have been had we ſtood with <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocency, for then our bodyes had had only<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam non moriendi er Hypoth ſi.</note> a conditional power of not dying, but now a certain im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of dying any more. Now, will not our eſtate be much bettered till we have once got this dying work over; we have cauſe every moment and in every corner where we come, to look for him, bed and board, at home and abroad, <hi>neſcis quo loco,</hi> &amp;c.<note n="(b)" place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcis quo loco mors te ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectat 90: omni locuto mortem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectes.</note> thou knoweſt not where death will look for thee, therefore every where look thou for it; ſometimes its approach is ſo ſuddain, that the ſame day, yea hour, finds thee in the ruff, and leaves a cold and breathleſs carcaſs,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Quem dies vidit veniens ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbum hunc dies vidit fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> jaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</note> this ſame death watching us every where tis our trouble, but when once he is come and we have done the work, he ſhall never trouble us more, though the gripe that he gives us, with his cold hand, may make us winch and tremble; yet this may ſupport us, having layed his hand upon us, he will lead us to the gates of that Kingdome, into which himſelf ſhall never be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to aſſault us more; and will not our condition then be much bettered, yes ſurely; that's a ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> They change ſubjection to a ſinning condition, for an impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of ſinning; what a happy gain this will be? as I do not look to perſwade the carnal heart, that knowes no other heaven but what the pleaſures of ſin, or delights of a vain world afford, ſo I ſhall not need to tell the gracious heart, to whom ſin is indeed a burthen: you remember St. <hi>Paul's</hi> dolorous cry, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. as a man pained and crying for eaſe and help, <hi>wretched man that I am</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſenſu miſeriae tangor,</hi> the word
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107602:9"/>ſignifies a man heavily oppreſt and burthened<note n="(a)" place="margin">Qui cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatum luctuoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum oneri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus permi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur aſſidue <hi>Mr. Leigh Crit. Sac.</hi>
               </note> with mournful calamities; or as the ſame Author, like one who haveing ſtriven a long time, is at laſt like to be overcome with his adverſaryes unleſs he be helped; thus he cryes out for help and deliverance, <hi>Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man that I am, who ſhall deliver me;</hi> now comes Death and he does it, he ſets this ſame poor ſtrugling, and almoſt worne out Captive free; tis true, grace deſtroyes the power, rule, and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſin, but it muſt be death that deſtroyes the being and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it: oh what would not a gracious heart give that it might not offend God, what a gain the gracious heart accounts it, to have power but againſt ſome one corruption, appears by his many tears, fervent prayers and ſtrong cryes for a victory; well, death comes, and that brings him a compleat conqueſt, as <hi>Moſes</hi> told the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites at the red Sea, concerning thoſe cruel and oppreſſing ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of theirs, the Egyptians that had ſo waſted and harraſed them with their burthens, and concerning whom they were now in ſuch a great fright, they being at their heeles with all <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Chariots and horſemen and Army, an huge hoſt; if <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſpeaks right, for he ſayes beſides all his Chariots he had 50000 horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and 200000 footmen; but what ſayes <hi>Moſes</hi> to them <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Your enemies which ye have ſeen to day, ye ſhall ſee them no more for ever,</hi> ſo may I ſay to the dying Saint, of all his corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and luſts, theſe enemies of thine that have coſt thee ſo much, they that have bedewed thy cheeks with tears ſo often, that have brought thee upon thy knees ſo often, that have foiled thee ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; be of good chear, thou ſhalt now ſee them no more for ever; never more troubled with a temptation to ſin, never old man dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in thy boſome more to afflict and diſquiet thee; Oh! oh! what a gain is this to the heart truly gracious: And this advantage does the Saint of Chriſt make by dying, that's a third thing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Yet again in the fourth place, they change comforts at beſt but fading, and ſubject to loſs for durable and eternal; ſo long as we live here, all our comforts are fleeting and withering, the beſt of them ebbing and flowing; do we ſpeak of outward comforts, alas, they are poor, looſeable things, <hi>autdeſerunt aut deſeruntur,</hi> they either go from us, or we from them, what one ſaid of fortune<note n="(a)" place="margin">Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trea eſt cum ſplendet frangitur.</note> its glaſſy, when it ſhines it breaks, may be ſaid of the world with all its beſt things, how many have theſe times preſented us with, that were once ſtored with them to good ſufficiency, but now ſtript and can call little their own, ſo for comfortable friends, relations,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107602:10"/>theſe are comforts, but alas but looſable; thou hadſt a dear wife, dear husband, dear ſiſters, brothers; but death hath made a breach, they are gone, and hath left thee mourning for them, like <hi>Rachel</hi> weeping for her children and refuſing comfort becauſe they are not; but what ſtand I mentioning theſe, go to the beſt of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, internal and ſpiritual comforts, their apprehenſions of Gods love, their evidences of a Chriſt-intereſt, the comforts of Chriſt's ſpirit, in compariſon of which, the gracious ſoul counts all the world as a little dung, and which he had rather keep than his very life; why even theſe, while we are on this ſide the Holy Land, while we live here, they are ebbing and flowing; ſometimes preſent and the ſoul is lifted up, tis in heaven while on earth, by and by all loſt, and ſoul all amort, crying perhaps after its beloved, but cannot come at him, <hi>I opened to my beloved but my beloved had withdrawn himſelf and was gone, Cant.</hi> 5.6. How common this with preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Saints, this was that which holy <hi>Auſt.</hi> experienced, and did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his ſoul againſt, <hi>Ne timeas oſponſamea,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ne timeas oſponſa mea ſi pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſper a te retrabat fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem ſuam, tibi venit &amp; recedit, venit ad conſolatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, recedit ad caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam.</note> do not fear O my ſoul if he withdraw himſelf from thee, he is coming and going, he comes unto thee for thy conſolation, and goes away for thy warning, and which of all the Saints have been ſo happily guarded with divine graces, as to preſerve his comforts at all times green and flouriſhing; no, no, the beſt of our comforts, tho' they cannot be loſt <hi>quoad dei benevolentiam,</hi> in reſpect of Gods good will, yet they may be <hi>quoad ſenſum &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in reſpect of our ſenſe and apprehenſion; tho' Gods loving kindneſs cannot, yet our ſenſe of it may be loſt and taken from us, which makes it very dark and gloomy with the poor ſoul, and turns his ſongs into Lamentations; yea but now comes death, and that puts us into poſſeſſion of ſuch comforts, or puts us ſo into poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our comforts, as that they are out of fear of loſing any more; when once we take poſſeſſion of our comforts above, our tenure of them ſhall run parallel, with the long line of Gods eternity; there we ſhall ſee his face, and alwayes ſhining, it ſhall never be more eclipſt, there we ſhall enjoy our beloved and we ſhall be parted no more; will not here be a happy gain? why thus ſhall we be gainers in reſpect of our eſtate by dying, and that's the fourth thing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And laſtly, they change an eſtate of need and want, yea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual want, for an eſtate of fulneſs and all plenty; ſo long as we live below we are alwayes wanting ſomething, take me a wicked
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107602:10"/>man that the world hath eſpouſed for its choiſeſt favourite, or take me the child of God, that he hath moſt enriched, let me ſee the face that will ſay he wants nothing; as for the wicked man that hath moſt, I warrant thee yet he wants ſomewhat, hath he wealth? he wants health wealth and health? wants honours, good name children, hath he all theſe, and thinks he wants nothing? ah poor heart, he don't know his wants, he wants God, without whom all his enjoyments nothing worth, <hi>quid prodeſt diviti quod habet ſi De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um qui omnia dedit non habet,</hi> what will a wicked mans All do him good, whiles without God the giver of all good, he wants grace, more precious than Gold, he wants pardon of ſin, peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſet him by, ſet him by, he is a poor wanting creature; but give me the Saint of God, 'tis he we would ſpeak to, come friend, thou haſt other manner of riches than the other, but doſt thou want nothing? oh God help me Sir, want yes; I have an hard heart and would have it ſoftned, I have ſtrong corruptions and would have them ſubdued, I have weak graces at beſt, and would have them ſtrengthned, I beleive and ſcarce beleive, hope and ſcarce hope, ſometimes have comforts, ſometimes none, my wants are great; lo here a wanting world, nothing but wants while in this world; but now comes death, and he goes where he ſhall want nothing, for temporals, no need of them, nothing for ſpirituals, all perfect: tis the ſaying of one<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eacilius exponi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt quid non ſit in caelo, quam quid ſit in caelo.</note>
               <hi>tis eaſier to tell what is not in heaven, than what is in heaven,</hi> I cannot tell you what the riches of it are, but to be ſure there be no wants there, Rev. 7.16, 17. <hi>they ſhall hunger no more, thirſt no more,</hi> and chap. 21.23. <hi>That City hath no need of the Sun or Moon, the glory of God lightens it, and the Lamb is the light thereof.</hi> No no, the Saints needy dayes are gone now, their wanting time is over, here's nothing but what is deſirable, and here's every thing that is deſirable, yea fulneſs of all deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs, and eternity to compleat all; when once death hath waſted them over upon that ſhore, they ſhall find nothing wanting to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat their everlaſting blisfulneſs; as I remember one ſpeaking of hell ſayes,<note place="margin">n="*" Non mihi ſi centum linguae ſint ora<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Ferrea vox omnes ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prendere formas, Omnia pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currere no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem.</note>
               <hi>Non mihi ſi centum</hi> &amp;c. which is Engliſhed briefly thus,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>No heart of man can think, no tongue can tell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The direful pains ordain'd and felt in Hell.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>So may I ſay of Heaven,</p>
            <p>Had I a thouſand tongues, I might not expreſs its full happineſs, will glorious Robes pleaſe? will princely Attendance pleaſe? will delicious Feaſting pleaſe? I could fetch Scriptures to atteſt all theſe <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:107602:11"/>dark reſemblances of that glory; but what ſpend I words when the Apoſtle, who was a little eye witneſs and ear witneſs, when he was caught up into Paradiſe, 2 Cor. 12.4. yet concludes its fulneſs of happineſs thus, 1 Cor. 2.9. <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have entred into the heart of man the things that God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now whether to change a barren countrey, which is alwaies in want, for ſuch fulneſs of eſtate, and unutterable plenty, be not a gainful change judge you, but this change do Chriſts Saints make by dying; And thus I have ſhew'd you in theſe five particulars, that Saints gain by dying, in part of eſtate and condition, one ſtep farther and we ſhall come to the uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As they make a gain of death in the change of their place, as they make a gain by death in reſpect of their eſtate and condition, ſo they gain in the change of their company; in this reſpect alſo death makes them gainers, and this I ſhall hold out unto you in theſe three particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt they change unholy company for company that is holy and pure, unholy company? why the Saints aſſociate not themſelves with ſuch here;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 6.8. <hi>&amp; Pſal.</hi> 119.115 <hi>Pſ.</hi> 120.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3.</note> doth not the Pſalmiſt baniſh ſuch his ſociety, <hi>away from me ye wicked,</hi> doth not he complain, <hi>Wo is me that I dwell in</hi> Meſech? does he not profeſs, <hi>all my delight is in the Saints that dwell on earth?</hi> I anſwer, tis true he does ſo, and the like do all Saints deſire; as man is a ſociable creature, ſo by his ſociety you may judge of the man, wicked men are for company like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and Saints for Saints ſociety; the righteous are abomination to the wicked, and the wicked are abomination to the righteous; Canaanites are thorns in the Iſraelites ſides, and pricks in their eyes; I would as ſoon gueſs at a man bound for heaven or hell by his companions, as by moſt marks I know; it was the ſpeech of a good woman lying upon her bed of ſickneſs, and under ſome trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſpirit, her comforts eclipſed; <hi>Lord</hi> (ſayes ſhe) <hi>I hope thou wilt not ſend me to hell, for there be the wicked, and thou knoweſt I never loved their company upon earth;</hi> Gods Saints had rather be in a deſart, then with debauched companions; Pſal. 55.6. <hi>O that I had wings like a dove; then would I flee away, yea wander far off, and remain in the wilderneſs,</hi> but though theſe be not the Saints companions by way of choice or option, yet ſo long as their converſe and walk lyes here in the world, they muſt have to to do with ungodly ones; tis true their fellow Saints are their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107602:11"/>dear aſſociates, the company<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they delight in, but they cannot ſometime avoid ſinners company too, for then as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, 1 Cor. 5.10. <hi>they muſt go out of the world;</hi> yea but now comes death and that ſets them among company pure and perfect, now they are for Mount <hi>Sion, the city of the living God, the heavenly Hieruſalem, the innumerable company of Angels, the general aſſembly, the Church of the firſt born, and with God the judge of all, with the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, with Jeſus the mediator, &amp;c.</hi> Heb. 12.22.23. Now they are in the kingdome which no unclean thing enters, where are ſhut out all dogs, and ſorceres, and whoremongers, murderers, Idolaters, lyars, with the reſt of that curſed rabble; this is Gods holy place, where muſt come none but holy perſons, <hi>called the Inheritance of the Saints in light,</hi> Coll. 1.12. <hi>the inheritance undefiled,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.4. where they ſhall have no wicked Belialite, to vex, perſecute, trouble, mock, reproach, or bark againſt holineſs and holy perſons, no, they are gone by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to a place of their own, and ſhall never more diſquiet thee, in thy eternal and uninterrupted enjoyment, of thy long wiſhed for reſt and peace: Oh what a gainful change is this to hearts truly gracious, company well amended; that's the firſt thing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Then ſecondly they change company of an inferiour and lower rank, for Princes and Kings ſociety; nay indeed none come there but Kings, all crowned perſons; <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. <hi>He hath made us Kings and Prieſts to God,</hi> ſuch they were here though their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was obſcured, but now they go to have their Crowns put on, ſhall be cloathed with their Robes, have their palms in their hands, and be ſet upon their Thrones and ſeats Royal,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.28.</note> Chriſt told them before, <hi>Ye that have walked with me in regeneration, ſhall ſit upon Thrones;</hi> and now will make good his word to them, therefore there inheritance is called <hi>a Kingdome,</hi> Luk. 12.32. Yea a glorious kingdome, a kingdome incorruptible that fadeth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; now 'tis come, it was long ſince prepared for them, and now they being prepared for it ſhall have it, Matth. 25.34. <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father receive the Kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world;</hi> oh little thought the world when time was, what honour awaited this poor deſpiſed handful, yea but now to the grief of their hearts, and gnaſhing their teeth, they ſhall ſee to what honour God deſigned them; their life was hid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though Kings children, yet they were in their nonage; oh with what a ſcornful eye did the worldly gallant look upon a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107602:12"/>poor Saint, too low companions for his worſhip; yea but now death comes, and the Saint hath the better of him, he is for higher company than ever he was, the King of Kings admits him to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to a participation of that glory, in compariſon of which, the higheſt earthly honour was but a Glow-worms ſhine, where Angels and crowned perſons are his everlaſting aſſociates, himſelf crowned with the ſame glory; and that's a ſecond peice of their gain by death, in reſpect of their company, but then,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And Laſtly, in the loſs of friends themſelves; yea their deareſt and beſt beloved, they gain yet dearer and more deſirable; 'tis true, they are dear friends, and dear relations that death deprives them of, rending the wife from the tender embraces of her beloved husband, in compariſon of whoſe ſociety, all other worldly friends are not eſteemed, rending the husband from the boſome of the wife, the flower and crown of all her earthly delights and ſubluna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry contentments, rending the children from the parents boſomes, who would if God had ſo pleaſed, redeemed their lives though with the loſs of their own,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.33.</note>
               <hi>O Abſalom, Abſalom, would God I had dyed for thee, my ſon, my ſon Abſalom,</hi> and how much more pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, the loſs of children gracious, were it not for the hopes of the one above the other; theſe are huge and ſore loſſes: <hi>Iob</hi> ſtood under the reports of a loſt eſtate pretty couragiouſly, but when this meſſenger of death came, <hi>Thy ſons and thy daughters were eating and drinking in their elder brothers houſe, and the houſe is fallen upon them, and the young men are dead, them</hi> Iob <hi>aroſe and rent his mantle,</hi> cap. 1.10. Yea but yet even here the Saint by death becomes a gainer, for it carryes them to friends far better and dearer, to God their beſt friend and father, to Jeſus Chriſt, like whom is no beloved, 1 Theſſ. 4.17. <hi>We ſhall be ever with the Lord,</hi> comfort one another with theſe words; it was the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one <hi>Carpenter</hi> a Martyr; <hi>My wife and children are ſo dear to me, that all the riches of the greateſt Duke could not buy them from me, but for the love of my Lord I willingly forſake them all.</hi> and holy <hi>Bernard</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>Lord Jeſus I love thee, plus quam mea, plus quam meos, pluſquam me,</hi> more than all my goods and poſſeſſions, more than all my friends and relations, more than my ſelf; to this love, loving and beloved friend death carryes them, I hope you will not think they leave any ſo deſirable behind them.</p>
            <p>It was a moſt brave ſpeech of <hi>Socrates,</hi> when his friend <hi>Crito</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:107602:12"/>perſwaded him, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſi vitam ſuam, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ut ſi vitam ſuam ipſo negligeret liberis ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulis &amp; amicis ab ipſo pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus ſervaret incolumem. Liberi illi qui mihi eos dedit curae ſunt, amicos hic diſcedens inveniam aut vobis ſimiles aut meliores, nec veſtra ſocietate diu caritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus.</note> that if he did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard his life for his own ſake, yet for his childrens ſake, and the ſake of his friends that depended on him, he ſhould do what he could to preſerve it; to whom he made this worthy anſwer, As for my children, he takes care of them who gave them me, and as for my friends, when I am gone hence, I ſhall find friends, either ſuch as you are, or better, and however I do look not to be long without your company too, you will ſhortly follow me; he was an Heathen, but I am ſure his ſpeech ſounds moſt Chriſtian; does the dying Saint loſe dear friends, it is their loſs, but not his, he is going to dearer: and that's the third thing wherein (in point of the company) he is a gainer by dying. And thus I hope I have cleared my Doctrine, and made it good that Gods people gain by dying.</p>
            <p>They gain by the change of their place.</p>
            <p>They gain by the change of their eſtate and condition.</p>
            <p>They gain by the change of their company.</p>
            <p>We come now to ſee what improvement we can make of this comfortable truth, to our own benefit and advantage, and the uſes ſhall be theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, learn hence the great difference between the death of Gods people, and the deaths of wicked and prophane wretches, there is not the thouſandth part ſo much difference in point of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirableneſs, between the ſeeming excellencies and flouriſhing pompe of the worlds greateſt darlings, and the low, ſad, afflicted weather-beaten eſtate of Gods poor Saints, in reference to their lives, as there is reall difference in their deaths and latter ends; we ſay death is a gain to the Saints, yea but <hi>non ſic impiis,</hi> not ſo to the wicked, to them? no let them try if death will advantage them, you make a gain by dying? yes, dye and try, death to the Saints, tis a reſt and refreſhing; but to theſe, as one ſayes well, 'tis like the diſtracted ſlumber of a condemned perſon, who anticipates his next mornings execution in a frightful dream. The Saints may ſay to death, as <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Ahimaaz, come in thou bringeſt good tidings,</hi> but the wicked may ſay to him as <hi>Ahab</hi> to <hi>Elijah, Haſt thou found me O mine enemy;</hi> beloved, by the rule of contraryes, if there be gain in the death of the righteous, then there is loſs in the death of the wicked; and poor hearts there is indeed: Shall I ſhew you in a few particulars, what loſs there is in the death of the wicked man; why thus then.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:107602:13"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, he loſeth all the hopes that ever he had, and in the room of them ſucceeds black deſpair, we cannot deny but there is a vain hope in wicked men of happineſs, a fooliſh hope that it ſhall go well with them hereafter how ever they live here; we would fain beat them from it but we cannot, we tell them 'tis a good believing hope, tis a holineſs reproaching hope, 'tis an Heaven debaſing hope, tis a Devil pleaſing hope, 'tis a ſin encouraging hope, and 'tis a ſoul-damning hope; all this notwithſtanding, they will hold it; the Devil hath begotten ſuch a blind fancy in them, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they go on in ſin, yet they bleſs themſelves and ſay, <hi>I ſhall have peace, God is merciful, and I do not fear but to fare as well as the preciſeſt of them all,</hi> and this hope may be ſo fine a ſpun thred that it may be drawn out to the very dying hour, yea but then it breaks; Prov. 11.7. <hi>When a wicked man dyes his expectation pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth, and the hope of unjuſt men is cut off,</hi> as one ſayes on that place, perhaps he might even dye in ſtrong hopes of heaven, but his hope and breath failed him together, <hi>'tis the righteous hath hope in his death,</hi> Prov. 14.32. the other might have it to his death, but not in his death, then farewel that, as one ſayes, <hi>the wicked hopes breathing, but the godly hopes expiring,</hi> Iob. 27.8. <hi>What is the hope of the Hypocrite,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">improbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> juſtus etiam cum expirat ſperat.</note>
               <hi>though he hath gained, when God takes away his ſoul,</hi> what is it? why it is a vain nothing, he would not let it go while he lived, but now he dyes it muſt go; many times the poor wretch if a little awakened, ſhewes you that his hope is departed before himſelf departs, by his dolourous out-cryes, ſick bed ſhrikes and deſpairing ſpeeches, but however beyond death no wicked mans hope can hold it, no his hopes are all loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They loſe all their peace by dying, but had ever the wicked man peace? God ſayes <hi>There is no peace to the wicked,</hi> Eſa. 48.22. I mean that quiet that they had in their breaſts, by their tame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Satan as their Soveraign, and from their ſleepineſs or deadneſs of their conſciences, that they ſtirred not to their trouble and diſquieting; this is now gone and changed for horrors, ſtings of conſcience, and teeth meeting bites of the never dying worm, they have hitherto been men very quiet all at peace, devil at peace never troubled them, conſciences at peace ſeldome had an angry word from them, as fine conſciences for the wicked mans tooth as were in the world, for they might do what they would, lye, ſwear, be drunk, they would ſeldome braul or ſay, why do you ſo; this was brave indeed; yes if it would hold, but it will not ſure: Now
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107602:13"/>that a dying hour is come, How is it now, what all quiet ſtill? no, no, now the dog is awakened and it will bark, now the Lyon is rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and will roar, every flaſh is fire, and every word a Scorpions ſting; oh conſcience, conſcience, it was long before thou ſpakeſt, but now thou doeſt, 'tis death to hear thee, oh could you ſpeak with the poor heart an hour after death, and ask now, what peace man? put that queſtion to him, is it peace <hi>Jehu,</hi> is it peace, is all quiet ſtill? you will find the caſe much altered, lo here the mans peace and quiet, 'tis all gone, all loſt; Then</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> They change their comforts, ſuch as they had, impure and mixt, but better then none at all, for pure torments, thoſe pleaſures and delights which they did enjoy, they are all loſt, and what but bitter pain ſucceeds them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.25.</note>
               <hi>Son remember thou in thy life time hadſt thy good things,</hi> hadſt them, but gone now; as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Rev. 18.14. <hi>The fruits that thy ſoul luſted after they are departed from thee, all things which were dainty and goodly they are departed from thee, and thou ſhalt find them no more at all.</hi> the man had riches, but they are gone, gay clothes, full tables, cups running over, but all loſt; <hi>Laban</hi> and his bags, <hi>Nabal</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is flocks, they are parted, <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> and his Boules, <hi>Herod</hi> and his Harlots they are now aſunder; all loſt. A great Lord ſhewing to a friend his great Houſe, and pleaſant Gardens, his friend ſaid to him, Sir, you had need make ſure of Heaven, or elſe when you dye you will be a very great loſer, all theſe comforts they are all loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> They change their wicked companions, which were ſometime the deſire and delight of their ſoules; for the company of Devils and damned ſpirits, <hi>Go from me ye curſed, into everlaſting fire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Devil and his Angels,</hi> there be their companions now, as the Devil ſaid to <hi>Saul, this day ſhalt thou he with me,</hi> time was when they would not be for Saints ſociety, I warrant ye they now would if they might, but now they ſhall not; no, there is a left hand company for them, theſe roaring boyes ſhall have roaring companions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> In a word, they change whatever happineſs they ſtood poſſeſt of, for completion, perfection, and perpetuity of miſery: wicked men gain by dying? oh poor hearts, <hi>peſſima mors peccatoris,</hi> the death of a wicked man is a moſt dreadful thing, as one ſayes,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mala in mundi amiſſione, pejor in carnis ſeparatione, peſſima in vermis igniſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> contritione <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 'tis bad in the loſs of all their worldly good things, 'tis worſe in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107602:14"/>Soul and body parting; and worſt of all in the worm and fire that followes it; all you prophane wretches, what happineſs ye look for, take it before your death; as indeed you do, crying, <hi>Let us eat and drink, to morrow we dye, come fetch Wine, we will fill our ſelves with ſtrong drink, and to morrow ſhall be as this day and much more abundant,</hi> Eſa. 56.12. or as they are notably deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phered, <hi>Wiſedome</hi> 2.5, 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Our time is a ſhadow that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth away, and after our end there is no returning; come on there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us enjoy the good things that are preſent, let us ſpeedily uſe the creatures, let us fill our ſelves with coſtly wine, and oyntments, let no flower of the ſpring paſs by us, let us crown our ſelves with roſe buds before they be withered, let none of us go without his part of voluptuouſneſs, for this is our portion:</hi> what gallant fellowes if this would hold? but as our Saviour ſald to <hi>Judas, what thou doeſt, do quickly,</hi> ſo ſay I to you, make haſt, make haſt, for if death comes, all's gone, oh ſad is the death of wicked and prophane wretches; they are loſers, great loſers; And that's the firſt Uſe: Again.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Learn hence the reaſon of that great difference, between the righteous and the wicked, in their entertainments of death, the one meets it with reſolution, holy confidence, cheerfulneſs; the other with fear, trembling, and aſtoniſhment; the reaſon is, the one knows he ſhall gain by it, but the other (as well he may) dreads a loſs; tell the Saint of dying, you do not put paleneſs into his cheeks: When <hi>Modeſtus</hi> Lieftenant to <hi>Julian</hi> that Apoſtate and perſecuting Emperour, told <hi>Baſil</hi> of grievous things (as he thought) confiſcation of goods, and baniſhment, and death; the good man anſwered preſently, all theſe are nothing; for confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of goods, I have nothing but a few old books and tattered clothes; and for baniſhment, I count the whole earth mine; and for death, that will but haſten me to God to whom I live, and with whom I would fain be; he could not daunt him with dying tydings; yea, but now tell the other of death, and you trouble him, you put him into <hi>Belſhazzars</hi> fits, when he ſaw the hand writing upon the wall, Dan. 5.6. <hi>His countenance was changed, his thoughts trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.29. <hi>Phi.</hi> 1.23. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8.</note>
               <hi>the joynts of his loins were looſed, and his knees ſmote one againſt another;</hi> the Saints of God are brought in, in Scripture, as men rather deſirous of, then dreading a diſſolution, <hi>Lord now let thy ſervant depart,</hi> ſaid good <hi>Simeon, I deſire to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, We are willing rather to be abſent from the body, and preſent with the Lord, Looking for,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107602:14"/>and haſtening to the coming of Chriſt,</hi> not dreading it,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7.</note> fearing and flying it, and the whole troop of Saints are brought in, crying <hi>come Lord Jeſus,</hi> yea they are ſaid <hi>to love the appearing of Chriſt,</hi> and to wait for him from Heaven; yea but now are wicked men thus affected towards death? no, and can ye blame them, they ſhould be mad if they were, death hath too ghaſtly a countenance for them to look at with ſuch an eye, there is nothing to them ſo dreadful in all the world as death; Now if you would know the reaſon of this, the Doctrine contains it, the Saints know they ſhall gain by it, but not ſo the wicked man.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But I have here an objection to anſwer, methinks I heare ſome ſay, but are the Saints thus affected to death, and do wicked men dye thus trembling, we often ſee the contrary as to both, the Saint fearful, and the wicked daring in point of death; for anſwer to this, as to both thus, and firſt for the gracious heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> 'Tis poſſible a pretious Saint of God to meet death with ſome reluctancy, and that from a double cauſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt they conſiſt of two principles, fleſh and ſpirit, imperfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſanctified, now the fleſh may prevail, and ſo far a natural fear of death ſurprize for the preſent, but let the ſpiritual and ſanctified part prevail, and ſo far death's fear abated; there is a mixture of unbelif with faith, ſo much unbelief, ſo much unwillingneſs, but ſo much faith, ſo much deſire, and the more faith the leſs fear; or</p>
            <p n="2">2. There may be a certain unpreparedneſs at preſent in a ſouls apprehenſion for death, and that may cauſe ſome unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs apprehending ſome unfitneſs, evidences not ſo clear, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance clouded; <hi>O ſpare me a little that I may reco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er my ſtrength before I go hence and be no more ſeen,</hi> as a Spouſe that is to marry an Husband, ſhe would be prepared for his coming, and though ſhe may exceedingly deſire his coming, yet becauſe things not ſo ready as ſhe would have them, perhaps ſhe may not ſo deſire his coming at that preſent; ſo the gracious heart, not but that he looks at death as gain, not becauſe he would not be with Chriſt, with whom he accounts it beſt being, but perhaps would be more fitted for his preſence, which he hopes to be if God ſpare him, but ſtill with a ſweet and holy ſubmiſſion to the Lords good will and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Yea but then for wicked men, do not we often ſee them go to death without any ſuch, car and affrightment, no ſuch terrours upon their ſpirits as you ſpeak of, Now, to this I Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:107602:15"/>
            <p>Firſt 'tis poſſible they may be ignorant of death and its conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, dye like fooles and beaſts without regard to what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, thinking when dead, there is an end of them, ſay not ſuch are ſcarce to be found among Chriſtians, for Il'e tell you the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of thouſands is moſt lamentable and dreadful. Or,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Perhaps they deceive themſelves with vain hopes, if it ſhall be well with them, and God will be gracious to them, the Hipocrite along time deceived others, and 'tis juſt with God he ſhould at laſt deceive himſelf; their hope may laſt till death it ſelf gnawes it aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,<note n="(a)" place="margin">O quam multi cum hac ſpe ad aeternos la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bores, &amp; bella de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſendunt. Eph. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> as one ſayes, <hi>many goe down to Hell with a vain hope of Heaven.</hi> Or,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Perhaps they are dead before they dye, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſome <hi>that are paſt feeling,</hi> feared; they are ſenſeleſs and not awakened, <hi>Nabal</hi> like, their hearts dead as a ſtone; as one ſayes, <hi>Many go down to Hell, waking not till they feel thoſe flames about their ears,</hi> could you ſpeak with any or all theſe but an hour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death, they would ſing another ſong.</p>
            <p>Now you muſt know,<note place="margin">19. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.38.</note> when we ſpeak of death being ſo terrible to ſinners, we ſpeak of ſinners with their eyes opened, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences a little enlightned and awakened, and to theſe the tydings of death are killing, I warrant you they cannot look it in the face, with their own faces ſmiling, and truly you cannot blame them; for what ſhould make a wicked man willing to dyer firſt at the beſt, they are uncertain what ſhall become of them, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> when ready to dy cryed out, <hi>I dye doubtfully, and whither I ſhall go I know not,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Dubius morior quo vadam neſcio.</note> and <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperour, <hi>animula vagula, &amp;c. quos nunc abibis in locos,</hi> oh my poor ſoul what places art thou now going into, why what then can make them willing, is it to be rid of ſome pain they feel, nay then they are well helpt up; no, no they may often in a rage call for death, as they do, but when it comes to, they dare not dye, and you cannot blame them: 'tis only the Saint of Chriſt dares dye, and the reaſon why the one wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes, the other dread deaths approach; 'tis the Saint believes a gain, the other dreads a loſs by a dying time, And that's a ſecond Uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Again thirdly, do Gods Saints gain by dying? let it be for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ſupport to all Gods number, what a ſoul-comforting point is this to all you whoſe faces are heaven-ward, <hi>to you to live is Chriſt,</hi> why then, <hi>to dye ſhall be gain:</hi> And there is a threefold account whereupon you may bottome comfort from this honey truth, as</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:107602:15"/>
            <p>Firſt, here is comfort againſt your own death, how may this kill in every good heart the fear of dying, doeſt thou upon thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the ſentence of death in thy ſelf, ſhrink and give back? for ſhame remember thy ſelf, thou'lt get by it, I tell thee Friend it comes for no harm but good to thee, It was a worthy Speech that <hi>Artabanus</hi> gave <hi>Xerxes,</hi> that mighty Emperour of <hi>Perſia,</hi> who viewing his huge Army of at leaſt a thouſand thouſand Men, drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up Rivers as they went, and commanding Hils and Seas to give way unto them, he fell a weeping, becauſe it came into his mind that within an hundred years, not one of that goodly Company would be found alive; to whom he anſwered thus, I would quoth he that were the worſt, for we endure more ſorrow by retaining life, neither is there any one of theſe or of all men living beſides, ſo happy upon Earth, that he does not often caſt in his mind how much more pleaſure there is in dying, then there is in living, I am ſure the Saints of God may truly ſay ſo, doſt weep to think of death? I tell thee my friend, thou wilt get more by dying, then ever thou ſhall get by living.</p>
            <p>I have read of <hi>Trophonius</hi> and <hi>Agamedes,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Venerantes Deum peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedem ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boris ſui nihil certi ſed quod eſſ topti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</note> who having built a Temple to <hi>Apollo,</hi> as they were worſhipping god in the ſame, they beg'd a reward of their labour and pains, and they would not ask any certain or particular good thing, but only asked, <hi>quod opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eſſet homini,</hi> that which ſhould be beſt for man, and ſayes the Author preſently upon the requeſt, <hi>mortui ſunt reperti,</hi> they were both found dead, beloved, for Gods Saints it were the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt good indeed, <hi>I deſire</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt,</hi> which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>multo magis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> much more better or beſt of beſts, <hi>Phill.</hi> 1.23. and that's the firſt branch of your comfort, namely againſt your own death.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Then Secondly, here is matter of comfort and ſupport a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the loſs of your godly relations, 'tis true, 'tis hard to fleſh and blood to part with near and dear relations, and not to expreſs immoderate ſorrow, truly but that we are inconſiderate at ſuch a time, if we would ſet their gain againſt our loſs, it would be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great ſupport: I am not againſt the ſending our gracious friends to the graves with tears, and grief next to tears for Gods diſhonour, and the Churches ſufferings, I know no better uſe tears can be put to, then to lament the departures hence of good men and good women; to let the world know its great loſs by their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval, wither related to us or not; and if nature ſomewhat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107602:16"/>for relation ſake, I think it either no offence, or very pardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; I plead not againſt our ſorrowing, but exceſs of it, as<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Naturales &amp; irrre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. Turbari lonum eſt ſed non perturbari, <hi>i. e.</hi> nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opere tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bari<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Maerori ſuccumubere animum deſpondere.</note> one ſayes, theſe paſſions of grief and ſorrow, they are natural and unreproveable, but when they break their bounds and become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate, then ſinful; therefore <hi>Bernard</hi> diſtinguiſheth between <hi>turbationem &amp; perturbationem, 'tis good</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>to be troubled, but not over-troubled:</hi> when we give way to the exceſſive breaking out of thoſe paſſions, ſitting down and ſinking in our ſorrowes, and le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting our greifs ſo ſwallow us up, that with <hi>Rachel</hi> we refuſe to be comforted; this I condemn and would ſtrengthen you againſt. I pray thee friend what is the cauſe of thoſe thy exceſſive greifs at the departure of thy gracious friends, is it thy own loſs or their loſs? thy own, be quiet man, he that took away one might have taken away more, nay all, had he pleaſed; is it their loſs? nay there thou art miſtaken, they have loſt nothing, but every way gained: Oh could our dead husbands, dead wives, dead Parents, dead friends, (I mean dead in Chriſt) that have changed a poor earthly Tabernacle for a Princely Pallace, Sorrows for Joyes, Earth for Heaven, Travel for Reſt, behold us here lying in tears for them, they would ſay to us, as ſometimes Chriſt to the daughters of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>weep not for us but for your ſelves;</hi> we are well, never ſo well, nay till now, never well; oh the gain that the Saints have by death, may bear up the ſpirits of their deareſt friends at their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with them; that's a ſecond branch of comfort.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And laſtly, here is comfort againſt all deaths Harbingers; your Croſſes, Afflictions, Perſecutions, and tryals, that on this ſide Heaven you meet withall, all changes and chances, all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and loſſes, wherewith this life is laden from the womb to the tomb, from the Cradle to the Grave, <hi>man is born to trouble as the ſparks flye upward,</hi> and if the Saints ſhould ſcape them that were ſtrange indeed, I hope while you live in your enemies countrey, you do not expect it; but be of good chear, none of them all can harm thee; how prove you that Sir? why thus, if the King of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours cannot harm thee, none of his petty underlings ſhall do it; if death be thy gain, theſe ſhall not be thy loſs, run therefore your race, though afflicted with hope and patience; thou mayeſt ſay of the worſt of troubles, or troublers, as he of that Tyrant, <hi>He may kill me, but he cannot hurt me.</hi> It was a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave ſpeech of <hi>Damindas,</hi> when ſome told him, now <hi>Phillip</hi> was broke into their Country, they were afraid of ſuffering grievious things.<note n="(b)" place="margin">O Semi vir inquit quid nobis poterit acerbe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidere qui mortem contemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> O you half ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107602:16"/>men, what need we fear ſuffering who have learned to deſpiſe even death it ſelf? why ſo, here death ſhall be your advantage, therefore none of theſe ſhall be your prejudice: that's a third Uſe, then,</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> 4. Fourthly and laſtly. I have only a word of Exhortation and Councell, wherewith I wil ſhut up all, that's too fold.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To all that hear me, and my Councell to you is, as ever you expect to have death do you a kindneſs, ſo look you be found of this Saints number, of this ſame poor ſcorned company of Saints; believe it thoſe be they that can hold up their heads in death, when others have cauſe to tremble and look ruefully, theſe be they ſhall get by death, when others ſhall looſe all, and whatever your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of them be, now you'l wiſh to be of them one day. I know not that ever I met with that man, that would not have dyed a Saint though he lived a very Devil, then with <hi>Baalam, Oh that my Soul might dye the death of the Righteous, and my laſt end be like His,</hi> but don't cozen your ſelves, holineſs in Life, hope in Death, and happineſs of death, follow each other; If not of this number, as ſure as the Lord lives, death will not pleaſure you, but ruine you. That's the firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the Saints themſelves, and my councell is, that you would endeavour after a full aſſurance, that your death ſhall be thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> to you; to know in your ſelves (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34.) not only by Gueſs, Conjecture, or Hear-ſay, but be able to ſay as the Apoſtle here, <hi>to me to dye is gain,</hi> without which you'l never be able to dye like your ſelves; but timerouſly and doubtfully, which though we cannot ſay but may be ſometime the caſe of a good Chriſtian, yet is much below his goodneſs. And therefore reſt not till you have got above dying fears, till you can ſay, <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth.</hi> In a word till you can end with this Text in your mouthes, and that upon a good ground, <hi>To me to Live hath been Chriſt, and therefore to me to Dye ſhall now be Gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now my Friends, having done with one Text, I know it will be expected I ſhould apply my ſelf unto another, namely to ſpeak ſomething touching our dear Siſter, whoſe pilgrimage while here, hath been exemplary, whoſe loſs is ſo much lamented, and whoſe life and death, I think if any could be ſo, hath been a perfect Comment on this Scripture, I am perſwaded that you all think, that <hi>to her to live was Chriſt,</hi> and if ſo, then ſure I am, <hi>to her to dye hath been Gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:107602:17"/>
            <p>I confeſs it hath been a cuſtome very ancient in the Church of God, for the living upon publick occaſions to commend what was praiſe worthy in the Dead, and to hold forth their vertuous Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to others, for their imitation, witneſs <hi>Nazianzen, Baſil, David</hi> of <hi>Abner;</hi> withall moſt infinite inſtances of the like exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, both from Sacred Writ,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.33.</note> and Church Hiſtory, and ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warranted, by our Saviour Chriſt himſelf touching <hi>John</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, John 5.35. <hi>He was a burning and ſhining Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not for partiality or by reſpects, becauſe Neighbours, Friends, Relations, or related to thoſe to whom we owe reſpect.</p>
            <p>Nor for Adulation or Flattery, to commend thoſe that were moſt vicious, a Sin in all, eſpecially in Gods Miniſters, who ought alwayes ſo to ſpeak and do, as if they heard that voice <hi>redde ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem &amp;c.</hi> give an account of thy Steward-ſhip, of all men it ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes them, by gilding rotten Poſts to ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked in their wickedneſs; Methinks it ſhould have ſtruck that preacher dumb, and filled his heart with trembling, of whom this ſad Story is related, who when preaching a Funerall Sermon for a Man, whom he ſtyled a Religious man, heard a voyce at the ſame time in the Church crying, <hi>Mortuus Sum, Judicatus Sum, Damnatus Sum,,</hi> I am Dead, I am Judged, I am Damned.</p>
            <p>If I know my own heart, I would not for a World, give a Title undeſerved, nor ſpeak with my mouth what my heart gain-ſayeth; <hi>Thales</hi> being asked how much truth differed from error, anſwered<note n="(a)" place="margin">Quantum diſtant ab auribus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi. Qui audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt audita loquantur qui vident plan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt.</note> as much as the eyes differed from the ears, and if at any time Miniſters find occaſion for an Encomium this way, they ſhould be ſure to obſerve that good and ſafe Rule Joh. 3.11. <hi>To ſpeak but what they know, and teſtify but what they have ſeen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have not been overforward this way when a publique preacher, though in ſome caſes, I think it not only lawful, but convenient, and if ever I might do it for any, I ſhould wrong the memory of this precious and worthy Saint of Chriſt, ſhould I not Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thoſe excellent Vertues; with which God had rarely endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her, above the common Size; I fear not to be counted a flatterer by thoſe that knew her well, in any thing I ſhall ſay of her, but rather fear, leaſt I wrong her memory in ſpeaking too little upon this ſuddain warning.</p>
            <p>True ſhe needeth none of our Praiſes, her works while ſhe lived, praiſed her in the Gates, and being dead (by them) ſhe yet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſhe would have deſpiſed them whiles alive, and wants them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107602:17"/>not now dead, but as he ſaid,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Laudes quia mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempſit &amp; quia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempſit magis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebatur.</note> becauſe ſhe deſerved praiſe, ſhe deſpiſed it, and becauſe ſhe deſpiſed it, ſhe the more deſerveth it; therefore ſomthing I muſt and cannot but ſpeak, and methinks it fareth with me in my entrance, as with a man comming into a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den where there are variety of Flowers, and therefore he knowes not where to pick, ſo amongſt her many commendable parts, I know not which to preſent you with. Should I but obſerve that Rule forementioned, to ſpeak but what I know, and teſtify but what I my ſelf have ſeen, I might break a box of ſuch precious <hi>Spike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> as would fill the houſe with a ſweet perfume.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt ſhe was you know a young woman, but an aged Saint, I may ſay of her as truly, as every the Emperour of his <hi>Piſo,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Hujus vita compoſita a pueritia</note> her life was grave and ſerious; ſhe was even a woman from a child, ſhe began with God betimes, remembring her Creator in the dayes of her youth, ſhe was none of thoſe who do<note n="(c)" place="margin">Flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo conſecrare faeces Deo reſervare.</note> conſecrate the top to the Divel, and the bottom to God, and having began, held on, an even and conſtand courſe in holineſs, confuting that Divels proverb<note n="(d)" place="margin">Angelicus juvenis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ſata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſat in annis. Quo ſempl rſt imbuta recens ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vabit ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</note> a young Saint and an old Divel, which as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſayes well (in his <hi>Pietas puerilis</hi>) was a proverb deviſed by the Devil himſelf, contrary to that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 22.6. <hi>Train up a Child in the way he ſhould go, and when he is old, he will not depart from it.</hi> I have known her a ſingle woman, then mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to her former husband Mr. <hi>John Clerke</hi> a godly Miniſter, and then to her late worthy Yoke-fellow now living, Captain <hi>Robert Fiſher,</hi> during all which time, never gave ſhe the leaſt fear, of having began in the Spirit, ending in the Fleſh, with too many in theſe late looſe dayes, but on the contrary, the elder the more Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the more years the better Graces, and her laſt Works better then her firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. She was of a moſt ſweet and courteous Nature, of as win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, affable, and obliging diſpoſition, as ever I met withall, of a friend endearing, and an enemy winning converſe, pleaſantneſs of ſpirit without levity, affability mixt with gravity, lovely, and loving, even to all, not knowing how to provoke any, a very diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of love.</p>
            <p n="3">3. She was a perſon of great humility, into which frame, till God hath brought a Soul, he takes no pleaſure in it, but humble in heart, high in worth, (as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> of <hi>Athanaſius</hi>) that firſt, ſecond and third Vertue, (as <hi>Auſt.</hi> hath it) who being asked by one, what Vertue was firſt and moſt to be deſired, anſwer'd Humility,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107602:18"/>being asked what was the ſecond, he anſwered humility, and what was the third, he ſaid ſtill Humility, that grace that carries a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an flying to Heaven, as one ſayes well, the humble man ſeemes but to creep, but he flyes to Heaven, of this knew I never any better ſtored, though ſhe had, (eſpecially during the time of her laſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,) of the things of the world, (wherein Fooles ſo pride them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and for which they ſo prize themſelves) in great plenty and abundance, yet like one reſolved to follow her Saviours pattern, of whom tis ſayd <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. <hi>Though in the form of God, and thought it no robbery to be equall with God: Yet made himſelf of no reputation, but took upon him the form of a Servant, &amp;c.</hi> So this his diſciple, outwardly great, inwardly little, rich in the World, poor in Spirit, which grace though it made her nothing in her own, yet it greatned her in the eyes of God and good men, Math. 18.4, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall humble himſelf as a little child, the ſame is greateſt in the kingdome of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. She was a woman full of mercy and pitty, a ſiſter-grace to the former, which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> coupling together, we will not part, Col. 3.12. <hi>Put on as the Elect of God, humbleneſs of mind, and bowels of mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mercy is deſcribed by Saint <hi>Auſt.</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Alienae mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeriae quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro corde compaſſio, quaſi poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ſubve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellemur.</note> to be a compaſſionate fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-feeling of anothers miſery, that puts me upon helping him ſo far as I am able, a grace that none ever loſt by; as they ſay the Dutch have a Proverb, Thefts never enrich, Almes never impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſh, and Math. 5.7. <hi>Bleſſed are the merciful, for they ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain mercy,</hi> an hugely honouring grace, that makes God the giver of our All, indebted to us for a little of it again, and we ſhall find him a ſure pay-maſter, and how largly was this Saint of Chriſt ſtored with this, her eſtate was large, and I am perſwaded her heart larger, no queſtion but what with lawfulneſs ſhe might, ſhe did this way,<note place="margin">Non pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt ſed pluriunt pauperibus impenſa.</note> and ſhe hath lamented it, that ſhe could do no more then ſhe did, for ſuch as feared God, and made it her great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that ſome ſhould have ſuch eſtates and do ſo little good with them, her will was to do good to all, eſpecially the houſhold of Faith, and where there is a will, comfortable is that ſaying of <hi>Auſt.</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Quicquid vis &amp; non petes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum Deus computat.</note> what thou wouldeſt do thou canſt not, yet God ſayes tis done, and a greater then <hi>Auſtin</hi> warrants it, 2 Cor. 8.12. <hi>If there be a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling mind, tis accepted according to that a man hath, and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that he hath not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. She was admirable for her patience, that grace that enables a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107602:18"/>Soul, cheerfully, and quietly, to ſubmit its will to Gods, and to bear what ever befals it in its courſe towards Heaven, ſweetly, and contentedly, becauſe God will have it ſo: her affliction was long and ſometimes ſharp, yet who ever heard a repining word from her, how ſilently ſubmiſſive to the divine pleaſure? her pain might ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time force her to groan, but never to grumble, having learned <hi>Jobes</hi> leſſon, cap. 2.10. <hi>Shall we receive good at the hand of the Lord, and ſhall we not receive evill,</hi> or good old <hi>Elies,</hi> 1 Sam. 3.18. <hi>It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good,</hi> or that of a greater or better then either, John 18.11. <hi>The cup that my Father hath given me, ſhall I not drink it,</hi> though ſo waſted, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at ſhe became a pittiful Anatomy of frail mortality, yet a perfect pattern of chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an patience.</p>
            <p n="6">6. She was of a moſt meek and peaceable frame of ſpirit, her <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning was not plaiting the haire,</hi> &amp;c. but with <hi>the ornament of a meek &amp; quiet ſpirit, which is in the ſight of God great price,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.4..</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> was uſed to ſay, that next to the Scripture, ſhe knew no book that did her ſo much good as <hi>Seneca de Clementia,</hi> and her Clemency was ſuch that her brother King <hi>Edward</hi> was uſed to call her, his ſweet ſiſter Temperance, I cannot ſay that our ſiſter had ſo much Learning as to read that Book, but ſure I am as to the practice, ſhe had ſo learned that, that none could exceed her, and from a better Maſter then all <hi>Senecaes,</hi> Math. 11.29. <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. She was a conſtant frequenter when able, and an affectionate lover of Gods Word and Ordinances; It is a great argument of an heart truly gracious, when it can ſay with holy <hi>David,</hi> Pſ. 26.8. <hi>Lord, I have leved the habitation of thy Houſe, and the place where thine Honour dwelleth.</hi> How often have I ſeen her at the place of Gods Service in ſuch weather, which hardyer then ſhe, and much her inferiours, would have pleaded as a tolerable excuſe for their abſence, and when there, how curious and attentive in hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, bringing as Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> cales them, <hi>Aures bibulas,</hi> and I may add <hi>Animam magis bibulam,</hi> thirſty Ears, and a Soul more thirſty, how relliſhing were Gods ſaying truths to her at all times, yea ſweet, as <hi>David</hi> ſayes, Pſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>19.103. <hi>How ſweet are thy words unto my taſt, yea ſweeter then honey to my mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. She was one of a moſt tender conſcience, that Jewell of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels, and infallible character of a true child of God, that ſoul-feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grace; a good conſcience is a continuall feaſt, that countenance
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107602:19"/>cheering grace, Prov. 15.13. <hi>A merry heart maketh a cheerfull countenance;</hi> and well might her countenance be cheerful, when her conſcience was kept quiet and peaceful; <hi>Euſebius</hi> reports of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs under <hi>Severus,</hi> that comming forth after a long and hard Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, they looked more like thoſe that came out of a ſhop of ſweet Oyntments, then out of a Priſon, they carryed in their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Divinum neſcio quid in vultibus praeſerentes</note> a certain divine Aſpect; no queſtion but it was that within, that made their faces ſhine without; oh how pleaſant would this our Siſter be, during her <hi>Lucida, intervalla</hi> her Mitigations of her diſtemper, pleaſant in her ſpeeches, pleaſant in her actions, which gave all to ſee there was peace within, the cauſe of this pleaſantneſs without this tenderneſs of conſcience ſhe evidenced, by univerſall care to pleaſe, and fear to offend her good God in any thing. I may truly ſay of her, as Acts 24.16. Her care was, <hi>to keep her conſcience void of offence towards God and towards Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have read of <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius Druſus;</hi> being about to build a ſtately Houſe; the Workman told him that he would ſo contrive it that, that none ſhould over look him or ſee what was done in his houſe, to whom <hi>Druſus</hi> made this anſwer,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Quin tu potius ſi quid in te art is eſt ita compone domum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ut quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid agam ab omnibus in ſpici om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus.</note> nay rather if thou haſt any art, ſhew it in ſo contriving my houſe, that whatſoever I do, may be beheld of all, truly I think could ſuch an houſe been built, an Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant fitter then this our ſiſter to have dwelt in the ſame, could no where have been found, I have known her long, but know not, that ever I heard reported of her any one action, or heard from her any word unworthy the beſt of Eyes or Ears.</p>
            <p n="9">9. In a word for her general practiſe of godlyneſs, (I hope and queſtion not) in the ſincerity of heart I am ſure in the unblame able<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life, ſhe was an Iſraeliteſs indeed in whom was no guil, one of the ornaments of her Sex; well reported of by all; yea of the truth it ſelf; free from the crimes of ſinful Age, <hi>Non ſine peccato, ſed ſine querela,</hi> I ſay not without ſin, but without complaint; and no marvel, for ſhe ſet the Lord alwayes before her; therrfore ſhe did not fall; the grace of God that appeared to her, wrought ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in her, that it taught her, and inabled her, to deny all ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and worldly Luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in this preſent evil World.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Shall I leave her in this reſpect, and ſpeak of her as a Wife; ſhe was her husbands Crown, Prov. 12.4. <hi>A vertuous woman is the crown of her Husband,</hi> a rich Portion of the Lords own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107602:19"/>Prov. 19.14. <hi>Houſe and riches are the Inheritance of Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers, but a prudent Wife is of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was one of <hi>Salomons</hi> wives, mentioned, Prov. 31.11, 12. <hi>One that the heart of her Husband might ſafely truſt in,</hi> ſo that he ſhall have no need of ſpoyl. <hi>She will do him good, and not evil, all the dayes of her life.</hi> Oh the teares ſhe ſhed for him while abſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas; and the many prayers ſhe put up for his proſperous and ſafe return, beſides her earneſt deſires to her Friends, that in their Prayers they would ſtill remember her dear Husband. Her deſire was exceeding great in this her laſt ſickneſs, if the Will of God might be ſo, that ſhe might live but till his return, once more to ſee him and ſpeak with him; but God was pleaſed to deny her, as he did his Servant. <hi>Moſes</hi> going over into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> though both to their great gain; taking him up to the land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> above, inſtead of that below; and her to a far dearer husband and head, namely Chriſt Jeſus; where this beloved Diſciple, now reſteth in the boſome of her beſt love, as I nothing queſtion.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Shall I mention her as a Mother, how tender and affectionate a parent, winning by love, not ruling by rigor; indeed ſhe had but one Child of her own, a young Daughter; and was Mother in Law to one more of her laſt dear husbands; who I dare to ſay, will ever teſtify, that ſhe had not a mother in Law, of a Mother in Law, but an indulgent, affectionate kind and endearing mother indeed, and if ſhe had travailed in pain of her, ſhe would not have been more willing to travail in pain for her in what had lain in her power to have done her good.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Shall I mention her as a kinſwoman, friend, ſiſter, relation, thoſe dear and mutual kindneſſes, that I have both ſeen and heard of, between her and you her dear relations, and that great love be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you; tells me that I ſhall but revive your gre fs, Peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture add to them which I am loath to do, and therefore will make an end, and ſet your patience at liberty, which I ſhould think and fear I had greatly tyred; but only for your great love, that I am perſwaded you all bear to the memory of your choice and dear friend.</p>
            <p n="13">13. For her death I can ſay little, and therefore will ſay nothing, ſhe removed from us to the City, where I had not the happineſs of being one of her viſitants, but I queſtion not but ſhe, whoſe life had been ſo exemplary; could not but finiſh that well ſpent life as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:107602:20"/>
            <p>To conclude therefore; I have read of <hi>Apelles,</hi> that he was uſed to ſay, that to draw the compleat picture of a beautyful woman, he muſt take one part from one, another from another, a third from a third, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and put them altogether; methinks this Chriſtian Gentlewoman, had followed this courſe in vertues and ſpiritual excellencies; one Chriſtian excels in one vertue, another in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but I ſcarce know any one neceſſary thing, that tended to make up a compleat Chriſtian, but in ſome meaſure it was in her.</p>
            <p>Well, ſhe is gone, we following, and in the prime of her dayes, and flower of her years, ſhe is ſent for hence, but the loſs ours, not hers: Life is compared to a Comedy,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ut fabula ſic vita non quam d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ben abb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert.</note> no matter how ſhort, if well acted; which how hers was you have heard, I know her loſs is much lamented by all neighbours that knew her, more by all her friends that knew her better, and moſt of all by her dear rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that enjoyed her; but ſhew your ſelves Chriſtians that are nearlyeſt concerned, bearing Gods hand, as quietly and patiently in her death, as ſhe bare it in her life.</p>
            <p>Your loſs is great, confeſt, but her gain greater; nay you have not loſt her, <hi>praema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtis no amiſiſtis,</hi> ſhe is but ſtept before, not loſt you'l ſee her again, <hi>them that ſleep in Jeſus God will bring with him.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.14. Follow you her example, make ready, <hi>Let your loynes be girt, your lights burning, and be your ſelves like them that wait for their Lord, when he returnes from the Wedding, that when he comes and knocks, you may open to him,</hi> Luke 12.35, 36. And then you'l ſee her again; ſee your wife again, your ſiſter again, your friend and kinſwoman again; yea where all ſorrow and mourning ſhall fly away, and everlaſting joy ſhall be upon all your heads.</p>
            <p>Where youth ſhall never wax old, where your life ſhall fear no ending, where there ſhall be no more ſickneſs to waſt and make pale, no more death to ſeperate dear friends, no more greif felt, no more ſigns heard; as <hi>Auſt.</hi> moſt ſweetly<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ubi juve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, ubi vita termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcit, ubi amor nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p ſcit, ubi ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nitas nunquam marceſcit, ubi gaudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſcit, ubi dolor nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur, ubi genitus nunquam audi ur, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the which place and time, the Lord in Mercy fit and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa o us All; and unto which in his due time, bring us as our Hope is; he hath done this our dear Siſter;</hi> Amen, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:107602:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
